{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Power required to drive a centrifugal pump is directly proportional to __________ of its impeller.", "opta": "diameter", "optb": "square of diameter", "optc": "cube of diameter", "optd": "fourth power of diameter", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The mechanical efficiency of an impulse turbine is", "opta": "ratio of the actual power produced by the turbine to the energy actually supplied by the turbine", "optb": "ratio of the actual work available at the turbine to the energy imparted to the wheel", "optc": "ratio of the Work done on the wheel to the energy of the jet", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The overshot water wheels are those in which the wheel runs entirely by the __________ of water.", "opta": "weight", "optb": "impulse", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a Kaplan turbine runner, the number of blades are generally between", "opta": "2 to 4", "optb": "4 to 8", "optc": "8 to l6", "optd": "16 to 24", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "If Hg is the gross or total head and hf is the head lost due to friction, then net or effective head (H) is given by", "opta": "H = Hg/hf", "optb": "H = Hg x hf", "optc": "H = Hg + hf", "optd": "H = Hg - hf", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Discharge of a centrifugal pump is", "opta": "directly proportional to diameter of its impeller", "optb": "inversely proportional to diameter of its impeller", "optc": "directly proportional to (diameter)2 of its impeller", "optd": "inversely proportional to (diameter)2 of its impeller", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A Pelton wheel develops 1750 kW under a head of 100 metres while running at 200 r.p.m. and discharging 2500 litres of water per second. The unit power of the wheel is", "opta": "0.25 kW", "optb": "0.75 kW", "optc": "1.75 kW", "optd": "3.75 kW", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The static head of a centrifugal pump is equal to the __________ of suction head and delivery head.", "opta": "product", "optb": "difference", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of actual work available at the turbine to the energy imparted to the wheel is known as __________ efficiency.", "opta": "hydraulic", "optb": "mechanical", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Geometric similarity is said to exist between the model and the prototype, if both of them", "opta": "have identical velocities", "optb": "are equal in size and shape", "optc": "are identical in shape, but differ only in size", "optd": "have identical forces", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The speed of a turbine runner is", "opta": "directly proportional to H1/2", "optb": "inversely proportional to H1/2", "optc": "directly proportional to H3/2", "optd": "inversely proportional to H3/2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A ship with jet propulsion draws water through inlet orifices at right angles to the direction of its motion. The propelling force of the jet is (where a = Area of the jet, Vr = Relative velocity of the jet and ship = V + v, v = Velocity of the ship, and V = Velocity of the jet issuing from the ship)", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Discharge of a centrifugal pump is (where N = Speed of the pump impeller)", "opta": "directly proportional to N", "optb": "inversely proportional to N", "optc": "directly proportional to N2", "optd": "inversely proportional to N2", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a reaction turbine, the draft tube is used", "opta": "to run the turbine full", "optb": "to prevent air to enter the turbine", "optc": "to increase the head of water by an amount equal to the height of the runner outlet above the tail race", "optd": "to transport water to downstream", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The power produced by the reaction turbine is __________ to the head of water.", "opta": "directly proportional", "optb": "inversely proportional", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Slip of a reciprocating pump is defined as the", "opta": "ratio of actual discharge to the theoretical discharge", "optb": "sum of actual discharge and the theoretical discharge", "optc": "difference of theoretical discharge and the actual discharge", "optd": "product of theoretical discharge and the actual discharge", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The efficiency of a centrifugal pump will be maximum when the blades are bent backward.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Multi-stage centrifugal pumps are used to", "opta": "give high discharge", "optb": "produce high heads", "optc": "pump viscous fluids", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The specific speed of a centrifugal pump, delivering 750 litres of water per second against a head of 15 metres at 725 r.p.m., is", "opta": "24.8 r.p.m.", "optb": "48.2 r.p.m", "optc": "82.4 r.p.m.", "optd": "248 r.p.m", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Theoretical power required (in watts) to drive a reciprocating pump is (where w = Specific weight of liquid to be pumped in N/m3, Q = Discharge of the pump in m3/s, Hs = Suction head in metres, and Hd = Delivery head in metres)", "opta": "wQHs", "optb": "wQHd", "optc": "wQ(Hs - Hd)", "optd": "wQ(Hs + Hd)", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following pump is preferred for flood control and irrigation applications?", "opta": "Centrifugal pump", "optb": "Axial flow pump", "optc": "Mixed flow pump", "optd": "Reciprocating pump", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The efficiency of a Pelton wheel working under constant head __________ with the increase in power.", "opta": "remains same", "optb": "increases", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The discharge of a centrifugal pump working under constant head __________ with the speed.", "opta": "increases", "optb": "decreases", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The unit discharge through the turbine is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Delivery head of water of a centrifugal pump is inversely proportional to diameter of its impeller.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The discharge of a double acting reciprocating pump is (where L = Length of stroke, A = Cross-sectional area of piston, and N = Speed of crank in r.p.m.)", "opta": "L.A.N", "optb": "2 L.A.N", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following turbine is preferred for 0 to 25 m head of water?", "opta": "Pelton wheel", "optb": "Kaplan turbine", "optc": "Francis turbine", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The speed ratio of a Francis turbine is defined as the ratio of the theoretical jet velocity to the peripheral speed at inlet.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The overall efficiency of a reaction turbine is the ratio of", "opta": "power produced by the turbine to the energy actually supplied by the turbine", "optb": "actual work available at the turbine to the energy imparted to the wheel", "optc": "workdone on the wheel to the energy (or head of water) actually supplied to the turbine", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Work done by a turbine __________ upon the weight of water flowing per second.", "opta": "depends", "optb": "does not depend", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum number of jets, generally, employed in an impulse turbine without jet interference are", "opta": "two", "optb": "four", "optc": "six", "optd": "eight", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a reciprocating pump, air vessels are fitted to the suction pipe and delivery pipe close to the cylinder of the pump.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Discharge (Q) of a centrifugal pump is given by (where D = Diameter of impeller at inlet, b = Width of impeller at inlet, and Vf = Velocity of flow at inlet)", "opta": "Q = \u03c0.D.Vf", "optb": "Q = \u03c0.b.Vf", "optc": "Q = \u03c0.D.b.Vf", "optd": "Q = D.b.Vf", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A centrifugal pump will start delivering liquid only when the pressure rise in the impeller is equal to the", "opta": "kinetic head", "optb": "velocity head", "optc": "manometric head", "optd": "static head", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When the speed of the pump increases, its net positive suction head (NPSH) requirement decreases.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A Francis turbine is used when the available head of water is", "opta": "0 to 25 m", "optb": "25 m to 250 m", "optc": "above 250 m", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The specific speed from 160 to 500 r.p.m. of a centrifugal pump indicates that the pump is", "opta": "slow speed with radial flow at outlet", "optb": "medium speed with radial flow at outlet", "optc": "high speed with radial flow at outlet", "optd": "high speed with axial flow at outlet", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A hydraulic coupling belongs to the category of", "opta": "power absorbing machines", "optb": "power developing machines", "optc": "energy transfer machines", "optd": "energy generating machines", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The principle of jet propulsion is used in driving the ships and aeroplanes.", "opta": "Correct", "optb": "Incorrect", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In the casing of a centrifugal pump, the kinetic energy of the water is converted into pressure energy before the water leaves the casing.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The speed of an imaginary turbine, identical with the given turbine, which will develop a unit power under a unit head, is known as", "opta": "normal speed", "optb": "unit speed", "optc": "specific speed", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For centrifugal pump impeller, the maximum value of the vane exit angle is", "opta": "10\u00b0 to 15\u00b0", "optb": "15\u00b0 to 20\u00b0", "optc": "20\u00b0 to 25\u00b0", "optd": "25\u00b0 to 30\u00b0", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In a reaction turbine, the pressure head of water, while flowing over the vanes, is converted into kinetic head before leaving the wheel.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Manometric head, in case of a centrifugal pump, is equal to", "opta": "Suction lift + Loss of head in suction pipe due to friction + Delivery lift + Loss of head in delivery pipe due to friction + Velocity head in the delivery pipe", "optb": "Workdone per kN of water - Losses within the impeller", "optc": "Energy per kN at outlet of impeller - Energy per kN at inlet of impeller", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The force exerted by a jet of water (in a direction normal to flow) impinging on a fixed plate inclined at an angle \u03b8 with the jet is", "opta": "", "optb": "", "optc": "", "optd": "", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In an impulse turbine, the jet of water impinges on the bucket with a low velocity and after flowing over the vanes, leaves with a high velocity.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The capacity of a hydraulic accumulator is generally specified as the maximum amount of energy stored.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The maximum efficiency of jet propulsion of a ship with inlet orifices at right angles to the direction of motion of ship, is", "opta": "40%", "optb": "50%", "optc": "60%", "optd": "80%", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The breast water wheels are those in which the wheel runs partly by the weight of water and partly by the impulse of water.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ratio of quantity of liquid discharged per second from the pump to the quantity of liquid passing per second through the impeller is known as", "opta": "manometric efficiency", "optb": "mechanical efficiency", "optc": "overall efficiency", "optd": "volumetric efficiency", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}